[Music]
hi everyone
we are back for another episode of the
usada pitch and this time i'm joined by
two guests our very own chief science
officer dr matt fedoric
as well as team usa swimmer and true
sport ambassador jordan willimoski
both of you are headed to tokyo for the
games and that's what we'll be talking
about today but first i
want to start by congratulating jordan
on making the olympic team
what an amazing accomplishment congrats
yeah thank you very much and thanks for
having me on of course
thank you so how does it feel to be
headed to your second
olympic games especially at their the
uncertainties of 2020
yeah just uh super thankful just to be
here
i think yeah with the uncertainty of
this last year and everything that was
going on i'm just really excited that
the games are taking place and
um excited to go over there and
represent the united states
awesome now matt you've worked the games
before a number of
but i know you're particularly excited
about this one so tell us more
yeah definitely avery i i lived in japan
for
three years when i was in my 20s so i'm
really excited to go back to japan and
experience the culture and spend time in
a sports setting with
athletes and i'm honored to be a
representative of the international
paralympic committee
and involved in overseeing the
anti-doping
program during the paralympics
that's awesome matt um and jordan what
does a
life look like as you're preparing for
the olympics
you know general training and everything
like that so
i typically we swim 10
10 pool sessions a week to wait sessions
and then some you know stretching dry
land physio and all that kind of stuff
so yeah a lot of work being put in and
right now we're at our uh
pre-tokyo training camp in hawaii which
is pretty cool so we'll be here
for a couple weeks getting to know the
team and getting some more training in
before we head off to tokyo
very exciting are you doing anything
differently because of covid
uh yes i think just this past year we've
done uh you know a lot of different
training uh not by choice but by
necessity so we've been you know
trying to find a different different
pool space and you know different times
we can fit in workouts just to
comply with all the uh code protocol and
stuff like that and then
um you know in terms of uh
covate affecting our training camp and
stuff right now it's
it's yeah it's pretty different than it
normally is you know there's a lot of
uh like self-checks monitoring testing
and we're
trying to kind of stay in a bubble so uh
yeah the team isn't really
leaving the hotel or anything like that
other than to train and i think it's
it's gonna be even stricter once we get
to tokyo
i definitely have heard of that and matt
do you anticipate
um expecting similar circumstances as
you prep for
the paralympics yeah absolutely i mean
obviously the health of
athletes and the japanese public and the
country are
top of mind so there's actually been
playbooks that have been published
that outline what you can and cannot do
and what to expect from a healthy safety
process
so things like regular covet testing
um contact tracing whereabouts
uh you know staying within a bubble and
not being
going out in public those are all things
that we all expect
and that are gonna be a little different
but i still hope the excitement of the
games and
the competition and the successes of
athletes will shine through which is why
we're all there
exactly and so we have these playbooks
going into the games
um but do you agree that anything could
change after the olympics kickoff
um things are going could that change
anything for the paralympics afterwards
yeah the playbooks they've there's three
versions that have been published so
um the olympics and the paralympics have
the same playbook and
obviously the processes have to be put
in place um
and they're standardized so we'll see
how things are going i i
anticipate that many of the same
processes will
carry over to the paralympics because
the same concerns exist
for uh athletes coming into japan and
participating and
and competing so um i think the safety
processes will
run through the games and hopefully
everything will run smoothly and
successfully
yeah let's hope so that makes sense
thanks matt
and tokyo bound person to tokyo bound
person
matt do you have any questions for
jordan yeah jordan i just wondered
from an anti-doping standpoint do you
expect anything different
for tokyo that yeah it should be
you know hopefully pretty similar but i
think you just gotta
kind of go with uh go with what they're
telling you just expect it to be a
little different
um i know they've told us we have to
list all our medications and
and try and do a bunch of different
stuff while entering the country to make
sure
we're complying with all their
regulations but i think for the most
part uh should run pretty smoothly and
uh usa swimming and stuff's doing
everything possible to make sure it's
it's super easy for us to uh
to you know comply with anti-doping
regulation and
to get tested easily and have it all run
really smooth
glad to hear you are getting the help
and resources you guys need
um and how long will you be able to be
in tokyo for
so we are at like i said our pre-tokyo
hawaii
training camp right now and then we
leave uh july 12th
for tokyo unfortunately i'm not allowed
to enter the village until i think about
five days before my race so
i'll be at a usa training center over
there until then
um i'll enter the village and then i
five days before i race
the fifth and then i leave the sixth
because there's
uh a uh 48-hour window
after you compete until you're allowed
to leave
that's crazy to think about so what's
the plan for
celebrating after you get back to the
states
yeah i think it'll be fun to see all my
family and friends again who uh
weren't able to make the trip over and
celebrate with them
very cool well that's it for today thank
you both for being here and jordan we
wish you all the best in tokyo
we'll see you all next time thank you
very much for having me hi good luck
jordan
thank you
[Music]
you